
{
	"version":"jm.01.20230127",
	"bbquiz": [
		{
			"question":"What is it called if you still have a pin or pins standing after you've finished bowling a single frame?",
			"a1":"closed frame",
			"a2":"open frame",
			"a3":"extra frame",
			"a4":"spare frame",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"It is called an open frame."
		},
		{
			"question":"Which hole in the ball is the most important according to the ball driller?",
			"a1":"Thumb hole",
			"a2":"Middle finger hole",
			"a3":"Balance hole",
			"a4":"Ring finger hole",
			"correct":"1",
			"answer":"Thumb hole. The thumb exits the ball before the fingers and if it comes out of the hole too early or late because of its shape or size it can ruin your accuracy."
		},
		{
			"question":"What's it called when your first ball hits the 1-3 pins for right handers, or the 1-2 pins for left handers?",
			"a1":"a brooklyn",
			"a2":"knee deep",
			"a3":"a pocket",
			"a4":"balls deep",
			"correct":"3",
			"answer":"A pocket. A brooklyn is when your ball goes on the opposite side of these pins."
		},
		{
			"question":"If you foul on your first ball, you receive a second ball. On this ball you roll it and knock all the pins down, without fouling. This is called a <i>what</i>?",
			"a1":"a strike",
			"a2":"a spare",
			"a3":"a tap",
			"a4":"a no-tap",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"A spare. A strike is when you knock down all the pins on the first ball."
		},
		{
			"question":"What's the maximum weight for bowling balls in standard 10-pin bowling?",
			"a1":"15 lbs",
			"a2":"15.5 lbs",
			"a3":"16 lbs",
			"a4":"16.5 lbs",
			"correct":"3",
			"answer":"A standard ball weighs no more than 16 lbs and has a smooth surface."
		},
		{
			"question":"What's the greatest number of consecutive strikes bowled, ever?",
			"a1":"28",
			"a2":"36",
			"a3":"37",
			"a4":"47",
			"correct":"4",
			"answer":"In May 2010, Tommy Gollick bowled 47 consecutive strikes. He stopped only because his game was over."
		},
		{
			"question":"A legal delivery is made when the ball crosses the foul line into <i>where</i>?",
			"a1":"the parking lot",
			"a2":"the restroom",
			"a3":"the other lane",
			"a4":"the playing territory",
			"correct":"4",
			"answer":"A legal delivery is made when the ball leaves the bowler's possession and crosses the foul line into playing territory."
		},
		{
			"question":"What's the highest number of 300 games by any player?",
			"a1":"57",
			"a2":"102",
			"a3":"135",
			"a4":"151",
			"correct":"3",
			"answer":"As of 2018, Fero Williams had bowled over 135 300 games -- by age 31."
		},
		{
			"question":"Knocking down three pins on one side, two on the other is called a...",
			"a1":"Top Heavy",
			"a2":"Greek Church",
			"a3":"Bottom Heavy",
			"a4":"Turkish Church",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"It is called a Greek Church, and it has an average 0.3% spare rate."
		},
		{
			"question":"If a gutter ball somehow comes back out and knocks pins down, what then?",
			"a1":"Group high-fives",
			"a2":"Doesn't count",
			"a3":"Score the pins",
			"a4":"Forfeit your turn",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"Any pins knocked over will not be scored. This is because the gutter is considered out of bounds and once the ball is out of bounds, it cannot come back in."
		},
		{
			"question":"The game is over and unfortunately you were unable to bowl a perfect game of 300. How many strikes would you have to hit in order to bowl a 300?",
			"a1":"10",
			"a2":"11",
			"a3":"12",
			"a4":"13",
			"correct":"3",
			"answer":"You would bowl 12 strikes because you get 2 extra balls if you bowl a strike in the tenth frame."
		},
		{
			"question":"If a bowler is not present, their score is their average less how many pins?",
			"a1":"5",
			"a2":"10",
			"a3":"13",
			"a4":"15",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"If a bowler is not present, their score is their average less 10 pins (unless league rules state otherwise)."
		},
		{
			"question":"What is the score when you spare in the first frame and then roll 11 strikes in a row?",
			"a1":"301",
			"a2":"290",
			"a3":"279",
			"a4":"286",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"A 290 is when you get any kind of spare in the first frame and follow it up with 11 strikes."
		},
		{
			"question":"When was bowling possibly invented?",
			"a1":"300 AD",
			"a2":"1700s",
			"a3":"5200 BC",
			"a4":"1366 AD",
			"correct":"3",
			"answer":"A British anthropologist discovered objects in a child's grave in Egypt dated 5200 BC that appeared to be a crude form of bowling."
		},
		{
			"question":"Who is considered the greatest women's bowler of all time?",
			"a1":"Portlandia",
			"a2":"Jane Wagner",
			"a3":"Lisa Wagner",
			"a4":"Lisa Kudrow",
			"correct":"3",
			"answer":"Depends on how you count it. But at 32 titles, Lisa Wagner holds the record for most career victories of any PWBA Tour. She is also the first woman to win over $100,000 bowling."
		},
		{
			"question":"Who is considered the greatest men's bowler of all time?",
			"a1":"Jeff Stryker",
			"a2":"Pete Weber",
			"a3":"Kim Jong-Il",
			"a4":"Walt Williams",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"Depends on how you count it. But Pete Weber has won 37 PBA tour titles, 10 major PBA titles, 5 US Open titles, and completed the Triple Crown twice (1989 and 2013)."
		},
		{
			"question":"Why are bowlers called <i>keglers</i> in Germany?",
			"a1":"Ich wei√ü nicht",
			"a2":"God said so",
			"a3":"Greg said so",
			"a4":"kegs (duh)",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"Bowling began in Germany in 400 AD as a ritual to cleanse oneself from sin by rolling a rock into a club (kegel) representing the Heathen, resulting in bowlers being called keglers. <a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowling#Ancient_history' target='_blank'>?</a>"
		},
		{
			"question":"Ever heard of Wordle? How many 5-letter words can you make from b-o-w-l-i-n-g?",
			"a1":"five",
			"a2":"seven",
			"a3":"nine",
			"a4":"eleven",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"Seven: bingo, bling, blown, boing, lingo, login, and owing."
		},
		{
			"question":"Which of these is <i>not</i> the word for bowling?",
			"a1":"Italian: bowling",
			"a2":"Finnish: bowling",
			"a3":"Hungarian: bowling",
			"a4":"French: bowling",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"The word in Finnish is <i>keilailu</i>."
		},
		{
			"question":"Where did a certain, well-known bowler drink too much while playing?",
			"a1":"New Jersey",
			"a2":"Washington",
			"a3":"New York",
			"a4":"Oregon",
			"correct":"3",
			"answer":"Rip Van Winkle drank with mysterious bowlers in New York's Catskill Mountains and woke up 20 years later."
		},
		{
			"question":"Where is the world's largest bowling alley?",
			"a1":"USA",
			"a2":"Japan",
			"a3":"Dubai",
			"a4":"North Korea",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"The Inazawa Grand Bowl in Nagoya, Japan has 116 lanes spanning 650 feet -- over 2 football fields. By comparison, an average bowling alley has 26 lanes. <a href='https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/p/AF1QipNf9_pa7Zzv7iEfUONuyJWuGso2yRoKg7zcHhHY=w1280-h300-k-n' target='_blank'>See a photo of Inazawa Grand&nbsp;Bowl.</a>"
		},
		{
			"question":"Where is the U.S.' largest bowling alley? (HINT: begins with M)",
			"a1":"Minnesota",
			"a2":"Massachusetts",
			"a3":"Michigan",
			"a4":"Missouri",
			"correct":"3",
			"answer":"Thunderbowl Lanes in Allen Park, Michigan has 90 lanes. By comparison, an average bowling alley has 26 lanes."
		},
		{
			"question":"Some high-performance bowling balls have &quot;MB&quot; on the ball. What does &quot;MB&quot; stand for?",
			"a1":"Major Bias",
			"a2":"Mass Bias",
			"a3":"Marked Bias",
			"a4":"Master Bias",
			"correct":"2",
			"answer":"Balls with asymmetric cores have the Mass Bias labeled on the ball. When drilling a ball, the position of the mass bias determines the ball's backend reaction also known as the shape of the hook."
		}

	]
}

